<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;अधिवबौद्धम् on त्रिपिटके विश्वासटिप्पणयो</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;अधिवबौद्धम् on त्रिपिटके विश्वासटिप्पणयो</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Contemporary vajrayAna</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/contemporary-vajrayAna/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/contemporary-vajrayAna/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For practical purposes, from the H perspective, vajrayAna followers (even dominated by non-Arya populations) are devatA-adoring, with confusions such as&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;slight echoes of the anti-vaidika bauddha counter-religion&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;placing the devatA-s in service of the bauddha mata&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;addition of shAkyamuni to their pantheon.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;deities&#34;&gt;Deities&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Locals venerate many devatAs, with a buddhist veneer. They thank and pray to them.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Some are ferocious, some gentle. Some are in coitus.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Representations -&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Little roadside houses (could be empty), with fragrant burnt grasses.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;consecrated paintings (thangka-s) and sculptures.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;A notable deity is the horse-riding shrIdevI; whom the driver loudly thanked on returning via chang-lA pass.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Curiously, mirroring paurANika religion, Indra is reduced in stature, and made to receive instruction from maitreya bodhi-sattva post-defeat.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Animal sacrifices to fierce guardian deities were common until the refugee dalai lAmA mostly stopped it all.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;covering-and-revealing&#34;&gt;Covering and revealing&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the thiksey monastery, the fierce deities like yamAntaka are covered (so as to not disturb the monks&amp;rsquo; meditations) except before the annual festival. My theory is that they are covered so that they don&amp;rsquo;t chuck buddha and just focus on the devas.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>H history &amp; prospects</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/H-history-prospects/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/H-history-prospects/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Pak Afgh central asia were buddhu - but fell to Islam -&lt;br&gt;&#xA;high fragility to invasion due to monastic focus, unlike Zoros, Hindus or Hellenes.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;B acted as a carrier for H knowledge (medical, divine etc..) in East asia - just as Christism acted as a carrier for modern medicine, science etc. in recent times. But generally, H (sans B confusion) spread independently in SE and Central asia.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;prospects-in-india&#34;&gt;Prospects in India&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In mainstream India, buddhism is (one of) the (small counter-)religions of outcastes and rejects (not so much refuge of the hyper-intellectual elites as it was before the Mo-s put an end to it).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symbols</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/symbols/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/symbols/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;dharma-chakra between female and male deers (representing prajnA and viveka) is reminiscent of the shAkyamuni gautama preaching in the sAranAtha deer park.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;stupas, where buddha&amp;rsquo;s body relics were once housed, represent his teachings (with emphasis on karuNA in mahAyAna).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
