<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Getting off on त्रिपिटके विश्वासटिप्पणयो</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/getting-off/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Getting off on त्रिपिटके विश्वासटिप्पणयो</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/getting-off/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>1</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/getting-off/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/getting-off/1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Chapter 1&#xA;Chapter One&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(i)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;To prepare for ordination all those worldly possessions I’d no longer need had to be disposed of, including my hair.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“I know what you’re afraid of,”&#xA;Ven. Dharmapal told me. We watched the barber as he first arranged his tools on a cloth on the bathhouse floor, then filled an ancient jam jar from the tap. The lid had holes punched in it for sprinkling water.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/getting-off/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/getting-off/2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Chapter 2&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Getting Off-Chapter 2&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(i)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Once the Auspicious One was staying at Anupiya. Anupiya is a town belonging to the Mallas. Now at that time the leading youths of the Sakyans had renounced the world in imitation of the Auspicious One.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Now there were two brothers, Mahanama the Sakyan and Anuruddha the Sakyan. Anuruddha had been lavishly raised. He had three palaces, one for the cold season, one for the hot season, and one for the rainy season. During the four months spent in the palace for the rainy season he was attended by female musicians, and didn’t come down from the upper story of the palace.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/getting-off/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/getting-off/3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Chapter 3&#xA;Getting Off Chapter Three  –(i)&#xA;“… These two extremes, monks, should not be followed by one who has gone forth: sensual indulgence, low, coarse, vulgar, ignoble, unprofitable; and self-torture, painful, ignoble, unprofitable. Monks, this middle way produces vision, produces knowledge, leads to calm, penetration, awakening, extinction. And what middle way, monks, is that? Just this noble eightfold path, that is to say, right view, right thought, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, right concentration. Truly, monks, this middle way produces vision, produces knowledge, leads to calm, penetration, awakening, extinction.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>4</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/getting-off/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/getting-off/4/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Chapter 4&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Getting Off – Chapter Four –(i)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;… there is a gradual training, a gradual doing, a gradual progress in this Dhamma and Vinaya. Just as a skilled horse-trainer, having taken on a fine thoroughbred, first trains it to wear the bit, then trains it further, thus the Auspicious One, having taken a person to be trained, first trains him thus:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Come, monk, be virtuous, live controlled by the conduct of the monk’s obligations, be endowed with right conduct and pasture, seeing danger in the slightest fault. Undertake the rules of training. Train yourself.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>5</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/getting-off/5/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/getting-off/5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Chapter 5&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Getting Off- Chapter Five – (i)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Once the Auspicious One lived near Savatthi, in the Jeta Grove of Anathapindika’s monastery. Late one night Rohitassa of the devas approached the Auspicious One and, in resplendent beauty, shed brilliant light over the entire Jeta Grove. Then he saluted the Auspicious One and stood at one side. So standing Rohitassa the deva said to the Auspicious One:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Is it possible, lord, that by going one can know, see, or reach world’s end, where there is neither birth nor decay nor death nor falling nor re-arising?”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>6</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/getting-off/6/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/getting-off/6/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Chapter 6&#xA;Chapter Six (i)&#xA;… the Auspicious One addressed the monks:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Monks, the world burns. And how does the world burn? The eye burns, matter burns, eye-consciousness burns, perceptions perceived by the eye burn, and whatever feeling arises, pleasant, unpleasant, or neutral dependent upon perceptions perceived by the eye, that too burns. And with what do they burn? They burn with passion, I declare; they burn with hatred; they burn with confusion; they burn with birth, decay, death, sorrow, lamentation, misery, grief, and despair.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>7</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/getting-off/7/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/getting-off/7/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Chapter 7&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Chapter Seven – (i)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Once the Auspicious One stayed at Rajagaha, at the Squirrels’ Feeding-ground in the Bamboo Grove. At that time a certain monk named Thera lived alone and praised living alone. Alone he entered the village for alms, alone he returned, alone he sat in private and alone he used the ambulatory. Then some monks told the Auspicious One of this monk’s lifestyle, and the Auspicious One spoke to a certain monk, saying, “Come, monk, tell Ven. Thera, ‘The Master calls you, friend Thera.&amp;rsquo;”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>8</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/getting-off/8/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/getting-off/8/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Chapter 8&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Getting Off –Chapter Eight – (i)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Monks,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;the untaught commoner might be disgusted, might he repelled, might be well rid of this body, born of the four great elements. Why is that? Seen, monks, is the growth, the decay, the appropriation, the rejection of this body, born of the four great elements. Therein might the untaught commoner be disgusted, repelled, well rid of it. Yet, monks, that which is called heart, mind, consciousness, by that the untaught commoner is unable to be disgusted, unable to be repelled, unable to be well rid. Why is that? For many long days, monks, the untaught commoner has cleaved, been attached, held: “This is me, this I am, this is my self.” Therefore the untaught commoner is unable to be disgusted, unable to be repelled, unable to be well rid.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>9</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/getting-off/9/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/getting-off/9/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Chapter 9&#xA;The lion, monks, king of beasts, comes forth at eventide from his lair. He stretches himself, then surveys the four quarters in all directions. Having done so he thrice roars his lion’s roar. Having thrice roared his lion’s roar he goes hunting.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Monks, hearing the noise of the roar of the lion, the king of beasts, animals and creatures meet mostly with fear, agitation, dread. Burrow-dwellers retreat to a burrow, water-dwellers to the water, forest-dwellers to the forest, birds take to the air.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Author</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/getting-off/author/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/getting-off/author/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Getting Off- A Portrait of an American Buddhist Monk&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Sāmanera Bodhesako&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Samanera Bodhesako.jpg&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Religion&#x9;Theravada Buddhism&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Other names&#x9;Vinayadhara, Ñāṇasuci&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Personal&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Nationality&#x9;American&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Born&#x9;1939&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Detroit, Michigan, United States&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Died&#x9;1988&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Kathmandu, Nepal&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Religious career&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Teacher&#x9;Ñāṇavīra Thera&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Sāmanera Bodhesako (born Robert Smith, 1939-1988; known also as Ven. Vinayadhara and Ven. Ñāṇasuci in his early monastic life) was an American Buddhist monk. Born in Detroit, Michigan, in 1939, he studied at the University of Iowa, specializing in Literature and Creative Writing. He embraced Buddhism in 1966 in India, where he was ordained at the Bengal Buddhist Association of Calcutta, and spent several years as a monk in Island Hermitage and elsewhere in Sri Lanka. (His autobiography of his early monastic life can be found in the book called Getting Off: A Portrait.) After leaving the robe in 1971, in 1980 he again took ordination, this time in Thailand under the Venerable Somdet Ñāṇasamvara (Supreme Patriarch of Thailand) of Wat Bovornives. In 1982 he returned to Sri Lanka, living mostly in the upcountry region of Bandarawela. In 1988, while on a return journey to the United States to join his father for the latter’s eightieth birthday celebration, Ven. Bodhesako died from a sudden intestinal hernia while in Kathmandu.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Glossary</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/getting-off/glossary/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/getting-off/glossary/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Glossary&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;anatta     not-self&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;angsa     one-shouldered vest worn by monks&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;anicca     impermanent&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;arahat     worthy one, i.e. one who has attained nibbana&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;araņņa     forest-place; hermitage&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;asana     (sk) posture, in yoga practices&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;asuras     demons&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;atta          self&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;ba          (s) no&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;bakshish     (h) gift, bribe, donation&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;beedie     (h) an Indian cigarette&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;bhante     sir (a polite form of address)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;bhikkhu     monk (literally, almsman)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Buddharupa     statue or image of the Buddha&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;cajun     (s) plaited coconut fronds&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;cankamana     ambulatory (the walkway used in meditative pacing)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
