<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Articles on त्रिपिटके विश्वासटिप्पणयो</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Articles on त्रिपिटके विश्वासटिप्पणयो</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>bAlagangAdhara religion summary</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/bAlagangAdhara-religion-summary/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/bAlagangAdhara-religion-summary/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://threadreaderapp.com/thread/1386316508452769792.html&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this thread, I will discuss the colonial invention of the religion called &amp;ldquo;Buddhism&amp;rdquo;. I will summarize some arguments from S.N. Balagangadhara&amp;rsquo;s book &amp;ldquo;Do all roads lead to Jerusalem?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I will quote some old colonial literature in parallel. Most people don&amp;rsquo;t know that the understanding that Buddhism is a &lt;em&gt;different religion&lt;/em&gt; from the paganism of Asia (also called as &amp;ldquo;Hindooism&amp;rdquo;) was a very late one. The early colonial literature doesn&amp;rsquo;t mention it. &amp;ldquo;Buddhism&amp;rdquo; as a separate religion was invented in early 1800s. So the discovery of &amp;ldquo;Buddhism&amp;rdquo; as a religion is tied up to the formulation of &amp;ldquo;Hindooism&amp;rdquo; as a religion. Balagangadhara argues that both of these efforts are inherently trapped into a intellectual prism, of how Christianity sees itself as a religion, in a peculiar self image.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lindahl: Trauma among Vajrayānists</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/somatic-energies_trauma_vajrayAna/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/somatic-energies_trauma_vajrayAna/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Somatic Energies and Emotional Traumas: A Qualitative Study of Practice-Related Challenges Reported by Vajrayāna Buddhists&lt;br&gt;&#xA;by Jared R. Lindahl&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Cogut Center for the Humanities, Brown University, 172 Meeting St, Providence, RI 02912, USA&#xA;Religions 2017, 8(8), 153; &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.3390/rel8080153&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.3390/rel8080153&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A qualitative study of Western practitioners of Buddhist meditation investigated unexpected, challenging, difficult, and distressing experiences. This paper reports on a subset of 12 practitioners within Tibetan Vajrayāna lineages who described energy flowing through their body, knots of pain, pressure or tension, and/or concurrent emotional changes. In some cases, somatic changes were appraised as practice-related transient states, and in other cases practitioners were given a Tibetan medical diagnosis of rlung disorder.+++(5)+++ Releases of tension in the body or subtle body also sometimes coincided with an upwelling of emotionally charged content. Practitioners reported emotional upwelling during subtle body practices as well as during other Vajrayāna practices, such as visualizations. While some practitioners viewed these experiences in relation to a normative Tantric soteriology of purification, almost all practitioners with a trauma history reported traumatic re-experiencing and tended not to adopt a purification framework.+++(4)+++ These practitioners were also more likely to seek additional psychotherapeutic or medical treatment to help resolve their practice-related challenges. The manner in which somatic and affective experiences manifest, how they are appraised, and how they affect the practitioner’s ability to engage in the Vajrayāna path depends upon many individual, interpersonal, and cultural factors.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Not nepAli</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/not-nepAli/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/not-nepAli/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Even Prasenajit says &amp;ldquo;bhagavā&amp;rsquo;pi kosalako aham&amp;rsquo;pi kosalako bhagavā&amp;rsquo;pi khattiyo ahampi khattiyo bhagavā&amp;rsquo;pi asītiko aham&amp;rsquo;pi asītiko&amp;rdquo; (Buddha is Kosalan &amp;amp; I too am Kosalan. Buddha is  Kshatriya &amp;amp; I too am Kshatriya. Buddha is 80 years old &amp;amp; I too am 80 years old).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;kosala&#34;&gt;kosala&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;He identified as &amp;ldquo;Kosalaka&amp;rdquo; (a person from Kosala, as opposed to Videha or Magadha) and his Śākya clan traditionally traced its descent from the legendary king Ikṣvāku/Okkāka/Iṣmaho.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pannobhasa On War</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/pannobhasa_on_war/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/pannobhasa_on_war/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;videoEmbed&#34;  src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=X1C95zAG5Us&#34; caption=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[[0:00]] [Music] [[0:07]] okay i wanted to raise some thoughts and you know see see what what you gentlemen think about it [[0:14]] as well about the buddhist approach or a dharmic approach to [[0:21]] international relations and there&amp;rsquo;s there are two [[0:27]] suitor references i want to expand on and one kind of general observation [[0:34]] the first is a suta on the the great mass of suffering [[0:39]] [Music]&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sermon failure</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/sermon-failure/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/sermon-failure/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://x.com/GhorAngirasa/status/1923214334811136446&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sermon-failure&#34;&gt;Sermon failure&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Bauddhas learned the hard lesson that merely imparting an endless series of boring moral sermons doesn’t do it for most people. Maybe a few may change because of their innate Svabhāva/proclivity, due to which they are open to hearing criticisms of their conduct and acting on good advice. But most won’t. If it was the case that moral sermons will change people just by them hearing such pithy words, this world would have been substantially better than it is today, for there has been no lack of pithy moral discourses or their exponents.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vanaratna</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/vanaratna/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/vanaratna/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The fifteenth-century #Buddhist monk and pandita Vanaratna lived a remarkable life that unfolded across the length and breadth of South #Asia and crossed the Himalayan range. As a #teacher, #author, and pilgrim, Vanaratna&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Y&amp;rsquo;know what&amp;rsquo;s insane about this dude? Of the multiple biographies and chronicles mentioning him close to his own time, we have a contemporary record of the man from his disciple Go Lotsāwa Zhonnu Pel (1392 - 1481 CE).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
