<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on त्रिपिटके विश्वासटिप्पणयो</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on त्रिपिटके विश्वासटिप्पणयो</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2006 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Mysterious early mahA-chInAchArya-s</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-04-30_mysterious-early-maha-chinacharya-s/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-04-30_mysterious-early-maha-chinacharya-s/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2006/04/30/mysterious-early-maha-chinacharya-s/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It is clear that the chInas have had contact with the Indians over a&#xA;long period and have imbibed various forms of Hindu thought. It is also&#xA;well-known that the bauddha influence on the chIna-s was profound from&#xA;the early phase of the foreign expansion of the bauddha-mata.&#xA;Especially, the emphasis on the desha-bhASha as against the deva-bhASha&#xA;in the transmission of the early bauddha doctrine resulted in a profound&#xA;change amongst the chIna-s, which corressponded to the shift from the&#xA;peculiar literary chIna-bhAsha to the colloquial chIna-bhASha, with&#xA;incorporation of indic terminology in translation. We distinguish the&#xA;spread of mahA-chInAchAra, from the early layer of bauddha spread,&#xA;because unlike that layer, it used saMskR^itaM as the main vehicle of&#xA;transmission. While the chInA-s and their Indian teachers definitely&#xA;used Chinese translations for explaining the texts to the native&#xA;chIna-s, Sanskrit with its paNinian grammar was the principle ritual&#xA;language. Secondly chInAchAra despite being borne in the garb of the&#xA;nAstIka bauddha-mata principally focussed on Hindu deities and ritual&#xA;beneath this garb. These features along with the biographical allusions&#xA;regarding chInAchAryas from India suggest that they were primarily&#xA;brAhmaNa or kShatriya scholars who had fallen to the nAstIka mata and&#xA;carried their internal tantric tradition relatively unchanged, just like&#xA;nAgArjuna, the nAstIka savant. This basic pattern lead me to investigate&#xA;the issue of the earliest texts of mahA-chInAchAra (in the middle China)&#xA;and the upa-chInAchAra-s (not of so much of later Tibet, but those of&#xA;the Turko-Mongol khaganates of Central Asia).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>5 skandhas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/5-skandhas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/5-skandhas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://x.com/blog_supplement/status/1976862256999587982&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The tathAgata probably saw his H rivals as equivalents of flat-earthers when he proposed his 5-skandha theory.  But perhaps it posed more challenges to his own successors than among the H. Yet after all the dust has settled, it still remains a fairly plausible theory, even if not the most parsimonious.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Buddhu hindu influence</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/buddhu-hindu-influence/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/buddhu-hindu-influence/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Also B influence on H yogis &amp;amp; thinkers of the time is notable (seen also in shankara, effectively a prachChanna-mAdhyamika-bauddha)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;virupa-conversion&#34;&gt;virUpa conversion&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A kali~Ngan and Mh/Kar mAhAtmya-s state that he was expelled by v1s for drinking beer. Typically the incident is located at bhImeshvara after which he become anti-v1/H&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve not seen Harris&amp;rsquo; paper but IMO too there was only one virUpa of note. I think he has however accreted some anachronistic elements from various layer of history. For example, I think he was indeed associated with the reign of the pAla monarch devapAla in the 800s. However, a later king govindachandra of RJB fame was tacked on to the story relating to his voluminous consumption at the bar.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cheap imitation</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/cheap-imitation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/cheap-imitation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://x.com/blog_supplement/status/1988113084515577969&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It has been said - rather incorrectly, to my mind - that &amp;lsquo;imitation&amp;rsquo; is a high form of flattery. Part of the trouble is that it does indeed tend to end up with inferior &amp;lsquo;knock-offs&amp;rsquo; pervading the place with none of the sophistication of the original. - CAR&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Yes sort of the like in bauddha plagiarism of H material in the religious realm.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DAkinI plagiarism</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/DAkinI-plagiarism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/DAkinI-plagiarism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It has been known for some time that the last layer of bauddha tantra composition, yoginI tantra collection, heavily plagiarized material from the shaiva bhairava-srotas and its kaula evolutes. However, while the term “yoginI” or “yogeshvarI” is the most commonly used for the goddesses of the corresponding shaiva system, the bauddha-s use the term DAkinI for their equivalents.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It is notable that in the early extant shaiva tantra-s, the terms like DAkinI and shAkinI are primarily used for malevolent deities, and they are not the focus of yAga-s of those systems. They might have a primarily negative connotation in these texts: e.g., the Damara-tantra-s (uDDAmareshvara, like affiliated with the bhUtasrotas) invoke chaNDeshvara to suppress the DAkinI-s and ghosts. We have comparable counter-DAkinI spells invoking unmatta-bhairava in the eponymous bhairava-tantra. However, DAkinI and shAkinI also appear as the names of kula-s yoginI-s in the vidyApITha class of tantras in the bhairava srotas, but even there, they retain a malevolent character and are not the most prominent group of yoginI-s receiving high worship.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Devas in buddhi tattva</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/devas_in_buddhi-tattva/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/devas_in_buddhi-tattva/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;doha-like&amp;rdquo; verses in the vein of those sarahapAda or saroruhavajra (these could have even been originally composed by him. Considered scriptural by vajrayANa practitioners, they echo a modern &amp;ldquo;rationalist&amp;rdquo; view of material of religion:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;indrachApa-taDin-megha-&lt;br&gt;&#xA;vAtolkA chAshani-dhvani |&lt;br&gt;&#xA;nisR^itA nabhasA sarve&lt;br&gt;&#xA;punas tatra layaM gatAH ||&lt;br&gt;&#xA;tadvad vidyAgamA sarve&lt;br&gt;&#xA;devatAneka-koTayaH |&lt;br&gt;&#xA;chittAd eva samutpannA&lt;br&gt;&#xA;chetasi cha layaM gatAH ||&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Rainbows, lightning, clouds, wind, meteors, and the sound of thunder:&lt;br&gt;&#xA;all these are produced from the welkin, and into the same they disappear.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;So also, all incantations, Agama-s (scriptures), and the many crores of deities&lt;br&gt;&#xA;emerge from the mind only, and into it they attain dissolution.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fall</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/fall/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/fall/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;To what would you attribute the resilience of the Jaina counter religionists in surviving the marUnmata onslaught over their saugata rivals?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is only hypothesis but I have some support for it: I think by the time the bauddha-s fell to marUnmAda they were a very elite religion with little lay support and heavy dependency on royal patronage. In contrast, jaina-s had a more distributed support among the spread out trader communities. The former support system died with Islam the latter survived&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Guhya-svachChanda-tantrarAja</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/guhya-svachChanda-tantrarAja/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/guhya-svachChanda-tantrarAja/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://x.com/blog_supplement/status/1830088013193285674&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The shrI-guhya-sarvachChinda-tantrarAja is a tantra transmitted by the kAyastha gayAdhara paNDita to his Tibetan acolytes in the 1000s of CE. It seems to belong to the bauddha yoga-tantra class (for classification see: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2009/02/16/nastika-notes-2/&#34;&gt;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2009/02/16/nastika-notes-2/&lt;/a&gt; )&lt;br&gt;&#xA;and features some of the anti-shiva rants that typify the developing body of the later bauddha tantra-s.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;It also seems to incorporate material from the kaula tradition but in a rather unusual form (Gentry&amp;rsquo;s translation from the Tibetan):&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>mahAdevI-vyAkaraNa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/mahAdevI-vyAkaraNa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/mahAdevI-vyAkaraNa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;(Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://threader.app/thread/1464492897059885058&#34;&gt;https://threader.app/thread/1464492897059885058&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Sometime before the 800s a shAkta text under a tAthAgatan garb known as the Arya-shrI-mahAdevI-vyAkaraNa was transmitted to the Tibetans. In it the cosmic buddha of sukhAvatI vyUha declared that the H goddess mahAdevI would become a future buddha &amp;amp; called upon the saMgha &amp;amp; others to worship her with a 108 names.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One has to ask if it was a missionary ploy on part of the bauddha-s to appropriate mahAdevI or whether they simply could not avoid the growing H influence and had to simply accommodate it saying it was being sanctioned by the cosmic buddha.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NAropA</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/nAropA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/nAropA/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While nAropA has also been said to be a firewood vendor, I think he came from an erudite background consistent with being a v1. As for scholarship of saraha, there is a recent publication of his doha-s with Skt bhAShya, but it is not in my possession right now&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Tibetan hagiographies like to play up Naropa as a subaltern yogi type, but it&amp;rsquo;s not very consistent with the picture that emerges from his actual works, which is that of a very learned &amp;amp; confident pandita. Hard to say how much his story has been modified.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>rupAvalIya</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/rUpAvalIya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/rUpAvalIya/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We first heard of a lankan text termed the rupAvalIya written in the 1000s of CE in a vulgar register of saMskR^ita in the works of Coomaraswamy Ananda. He thought is a H text. It has never been published but snippets have been described by him &amp;amp; lankan authors.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It is clear that it is text descending from a H smArta-shilpa source (perhaps of kali~Ngan vintage) that has been reworked into a bauddha context. That is clear because it devotes considerable detail to the iconography of avalokiteshvara in his different forms popular in old lanka. But this bauddha deity is embedded within an extensive iconographic account covering sarasvatI; brahman; various forms of rudra &amp;amp; rudrANI; skanda&amp;amp; vinAyaka; various vibhava-s of viShNu&amp;amp; lakShmI &amp;amp; interestingly vaTuka. Thus it is mostly standard smArta type rUpamaNDana but the emphasis on vaTuka-bhairava independent of skanda is notable &amp;amp; points to a lateral influence from a kaula tradition. It also gives the specifications of other ornamental figures like makara-s, horses, elephants&amp;amp; the like.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>sarahapAda</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/sarahapAda/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/sarahapAda/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://x.com/blog_supplement/status/1986962618733457457&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Some of his intimate knowledge on traditions typically preserved among v1s suggests that sarahapAda was probably a fallen v1 rather than a larper. However, his subversion of v1 orthopraxy could be seen in a similar vein as how modern v1s are overrepresented in leadership positions in anti-H movements.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;shrikirtis-student&#34;&gt;shrIkIrti&amp;rsquo;s student?&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The tale of the mahAbrAhmaNa sarahapAda from a Tibetan source. (adapted from Guenther and Schaeffer&amp;rsquo;s translations from the Tibetan)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>shiva in kAraNDavyUha</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/shiva-in-kAraNDavyUha/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/shiva-in-kAraNDavyUha/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The karaNDavyUha a counter-religious saugata text states that after emitting the deva-s from various parts of his body avalokiteshvara told rudra who had emerged from his forehead (lalATAn maheshvaraH |) that:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;भविष्यसि त्वं महेश्वरः कलियुगे प्रतिपन्ने कष्ट-सत्त्व-धातु-समुत्पन्न आदिदेव, आख्यायसे स्रष्टारं कर्तारम् +++(इव)+++।&lt;br&gt;&#xA;at the start of the kaliyuga he would be known as the primal god who is the creater &amp;amp; agent of existence in the troubled sentient beings.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ते सर्वसत्त्वा बोधिमार्गेण विप्रहीणा भविष्यन्ति&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Those sentient beings are will become uneducated in the bauddhamata.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;य ईदृश-पृथग्-जनेषु सत्त्वेषु सांकथ्यं कुर्वन्ति॥&#xA;Among such ordinary people &amp;amp; beings a teaching would be made.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>vajrayAna-popularity</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/vajrayAna-popularity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/vajrayAna-popularity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For every hundred students there are a thousand teachers,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;And nobody listens to the divine dharma.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;For every village, there are ten masters,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;And the number of vajra assistants is uncountable&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Translation of a Tibetan verse from Dunhuang by van Schaik&#xA;Show how unpopular the old the old school bikShu-oriented tAthAgatan tradition was relative the rising vajrayAna imitations of H tradition. The monastic nAstika ultimately had little to offer to the masses despite claiming to be vehicle for the alleviation of duHkha.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VirUpa &amp; chinamastA</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/virUpa_chinamastA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/virUpa_chinamastA/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://x.com/blog_supplement/status/2010224709485416676&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There are unpublished manuscripts&lt;br&gt;&#xA;that suggest that the bauddha siddha virUpa of anti-H disposition&lt;br&gt;&#xA;was a worshiper and siddha of the ChinnamastA/ChinnamuNDA mantra-s.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;He composed at least two prayoga manuals for this goddess&lt;br&gt;&#xA;with a homa performed using unclean substances&lt;br&gt;&#xA;whose mention would offend modern H.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It appears likely, based on the royal martial rites, that he composed one of those for the pAla monarch devapAla (ruled 810-850 CE).&lt;br&gt;&#xA;There is some evidence that he might have been associated with a chief in central India (centered on mahArAShTra)&lt;br&gt;&#xA;when he was still a H yogin.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>vyAsa-paripRchChA</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/vyAsa-paripRchChA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/vyAsa-paripRchChA/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The saugata-s created a text known as the R^iShi-vyAsa-paripR^ichChA&lt;br&gt;&#xA;where they had vyAsa surnamed KR^iShNa-gandhavatI-putra come to the tathAgata to learn from him.+++(5)+++&lt;br&gt;&#xA;He is said to have been accompanied by several famous v1s like R^ishyashR^i~Nga and agni and kumAra.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Sanskrit original of the text has been lost in India but translations into Chinese and Tibetan survive to date. dAnashIla is said to have transmitted it to Tibet.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;indra&#34;&gt;Indra&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In it, an account of indra is given thus (with the typical bauddha ill-intent of belittling supreme H deities):&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>सुबाहु-परिपृच्छा</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/subAhu-paripRchChA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/tipiTaka/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/subAhu-paripRchChA/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;subAhu-pari-pR^ichCha is a kriyAtantra of the saugata-nAstika-s,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;whose Skt original has been lost&lt;br&gt;&#xA;but a translation into Tibetan survives.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;It has the following anti-V1 message that would warm the cockles of the nIladrApin types.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Translated from the Tibetan it goes :&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“They should live near a pleasant town,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;not too close or too far,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Where food and drink are available,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;and shUdras predominate.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;It should be hospitable to guests,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;And without brAhmaNa-s of other traditions.&amp;quot;+++(5)+++&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
